Guide to the Irving Sonn Papers, 1963-1977 and undated RL.01232
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Irving Sonn papers
1963-1977 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sonn, Irving
RL.01232
3.25 Linear Feet
Irving Sonn was a copy writer for several advertising agencies including: Ted Bates & Co.; Ogilvy & Mather; Compton Advertising, Inc.; and Needham, Harper & Steers. The Irving Sonn Papers span the years 1963-1977 and contain general correspondence, clippings, memorabilia, photographs and presentation slides that primarily document the periods of Sonn's employment at Ted Bates & Co. and Needham, Harper & Steers. Also includes recordings of advertising spots and jingles in a variety of formats, including audiotape and cassettes; VHS and Umatic videocassettes; and 16mm film. Clients include: Burger King; Kodak; Kentucky Fried Chicken; and Toyota. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
2000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Irving Sonn Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2004.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1926 Born
1949 Graduated from New York University; worked as news clerk at the New York Times
1955 Began employment at Cortez F. Enloe, a company specializing in ethical drug advertising
1957 Joined Ted Bates & Co.
1960 Copy Chief and Vice President, Compton Advertising, Inc. Worked on the Proctor & Gamble; Brown & Williamson; Pertussin; and Sterling Drug accounts
1963 Vice President, Associate Creative Director and Copy Group Head, Ogilvy, Benson & Mather
1965 Named the first New York Creative Director at Needham, Harper & Steers
1971 Rejoined Ted Bates & Co.
1979 Left Ted Bates & Co. Founded his own advertising boutique, Irv Sonn Advertising, Inc.
1980-1985 Executive Creative Director, McCann-Erickson, San Francisco
1992 Died, Monterey, Calif.
Collection Overview
The Irving Sonn Papers Span the years 1963-1977 and contain general correspondence, clippings, memorabilia, photographs and presentation slides that primarily document the periods of Sonn's employment at Ted Bates & Co. and Needham, Harper & Steers. Also includes recordings of advertising spots and jingles in a variety of formats, including audiotape and cassettes; VHS and Umatic videocassettes; and 16mm film. Clients include Burger King; Kodak; Kentucky Fried Chicken; and Toyota.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: General Files, Slides, Audiovisual Materials and Plaques and Trophies. The General Files series contains correspondence, presentation scripts, clippings, awards ceremony programs and photographs primarily related to Sonn's employment at Ted Bates & Co. The Slides series contains slides used in print advertising campaigns of Ted Bates clients. Also includes slides for speeches and general market presentations, such as toiletries, household products, and food. The Audiovisual Materials series contains audio and videotapes of advertising spots, out takes, songs and jingles related to Ted Bates & Co. clients. The Plaques and Trophies series contains award plaques and trophies won by the Needham, Harper & Steers agency.
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records
J. Walter Thompson Company. Account Files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Advertising Vertical Files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Corporation Vertical Files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic Advertisements Collection
Materials related to Compton Advertising may be found in:
O. Milton Gossett Papers
Walter Weir Papers
Materials related to Ogilvy Benson & Mather may be found in:
Jock Elliott Papers
David B. McCall Papers
William E. Phillips Papers
Joel Raphaelson Papers
Robert S. Smith Papers
Materials related to other advertising Creative Directors may be found in:
Jim Brown Papers
Gene Federico Papers
Kensinger Jones Papers
Sheldon Sosna Papers
Anthony Weir Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Colin Dawkins Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. John F. Dignam Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Wallace Elton Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Arnold Grisman Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Edgar Hatcher Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Bertram Metter Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. George Black Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Wilfried Henkel Papers
Slides (photographs); Clippings (information artifacts); Motion pictures (visual works); Advertising -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- United States -- History; Videocassettes; Audiotapes; 16mm; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising executives; Memorabilia; Audiocassettes; Photographs; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Kentucky Fried Chicken (Firm); Needham, Harper, and Steers Advertising; Sonn, Irving, 1926-1992; Ted Bates Advertising; Toyota Jid?sha K?gy? Kabushiki Kaisha; Eastman Kodak Company; Burger King Corporation
- General files, 1963-1977 and undated, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains correspondence, presentation scripts, clippings and photographs primarily related to Sonn's employment at Ted Bates & Co. Also includes awards won by Sonn.
  - Advertising Writers Association of New York Award, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Clio Awards, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and a meeting schedule, 1977 and undated (Box 1)
  - Diaper Wonder Book, slide show script, undated (Box 1)
  - Kentucky Fried Chicken Recommendations, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, advertising magazines, 1968-1977 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Presentation to Burger King, 1976, Aug, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Ted Bates & Company, company information booklet, undated (Box 1)
  - Ted Bates Unique Selling Proposition, A Disciplined Philosophy of Advertising that Maximizes Sales Effectiveness, undated (Box 1)
- Slides, 1974-1977 and undated, 2 boxes
  Series contains slides used in print advertising campaigns of various Ted Bates clients. Also includes slides for speeches and general market presentations, such as toiletries, household and drugs. Clients represented include Amtrak, Chevy, Burger King, Colgate, Datsun, Hertz, Hills Bros., J.C. Penney, Kentucky Fried Chicken, Kodak, Kool, Listerine, Maybelline, McDonald's, Ortho, Panasonic, Pizza Hut, Prudential, Sheraton, Singer, Toyota, and the U.S. Navy, among others. Many of the times came organized in wonder books of slides devoted to particular clients or topics.
  - A-Z miscellaneous, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    [Includes Flair, Ital Line, Jordan, Bufferin, Calgon, Chase Manhattan, Crazy Canadian, Davies County, Facelle, Manhattan Shirts, Matsushita Electric, Mars Corp., Industrial National Bank, Nair, NY Clearing House, Ocean Spray, RCA, Roses Lime Juice, Schmidts, Schweppes, Upjohn, Warner Lambert, Expeed, Xerox, and Yardley.]
  - Airline, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Allied Van, undated (Box 2)
  - Amtrak, undated (Box 2)
  - Apex, undated (Box 2)
  - Beaulieu speech, undated (Box 2)
  - Burger King, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Burlington, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Case studies, undated (Box 2)
  - Chevy trucks, undated (Box 2)
  - Colgate, undated (Box 2)
  - Datsun, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Disposable diapers, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Disposable diapers, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Electrolux, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Far East presentation, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Food, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Gasoline, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - General development, undated (Box 2)
  - Gino, undated (Box 2)
  - Hamm's Beer, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Hertz, undated (Box 2)
  - Hills Bros., undated (Box 2)
  - Household and drugs, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - I.T.T., undated (Box 2)
  - J.C. Penney, undated (Box 2)
  - Julius Wile Benedictine, Wonder Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Kentucky Fried Chicken, undated (Box 3)
  - Kodak, Wonder Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Kool, undated (Box 3)
  - Listerine, undated (Box 3)
  - Maybelline (Coppertone), undated (Box 3)
  - McDonald's, undated (Box 3)
  - National Airlines, Wonder Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Ortho, undated (Box 3)
  - Panasonic, undated (Box 3)
  - Pfizer, Visine and Swedish Tan, undated (Box 3)
  - Pizza Hut, Wonder Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Post Office, undated (Box 3)
  - Prudential, undated (Box 3)
  - Publishers Clearing House, undated (Box 3)
  - Puerto Rico, Wonder Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Railpax, Wonder Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Selling in the 70s, undated (Box 3)
  - Sheraton, undated (Box 3)
  - Singer, Wonder Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Standard Brands, Blue Bonnet, Egg Beaters, undated (Box 3)
  - Toiletries, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Toyota, undated (Box 3)
  - Toyota, presentation, 1975 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Navy, undated (Box 3)
  - U.S.P. Charts, undated (Box 3)
- Audiovisual materials 1967-1977 and undated
  Contains audio and moving image resources, including dvertising spots, out takes, songs and jingles related to Ted Bates & Co. clients. Formats include open reel audio tapes, audiocassettes, videocassettes, and 16mm film.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Analog audiovisual materials require digitization prior to playback. Please contact Research Services for further information.
  - Audio
    - Burger King, Black Radio, circa 1976
      Scope and Contents
      1. Mean Joe Green; 2. Wilma Rudolf; 3. Naomi Simi; 4. Earl Monroe; 5. Donut - Male Singer; 6. Donut - Female Singer
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0001)
    - Burger King, Everything's a Whopper at Burger King, circa 1976
      1. First Day; 2. Shiek; 3. Hillbilly; 4. Tablecloth; 5. Report Card; 6. School Bus; 7. Simon Sez
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0002)
    - Burger King, Fresh Food, Not Just Fast Food, circa 1976
      1. Too Fast; 2. Steak - Wise Guy; 3. Bob Jones; 4. Freshness
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape, copy 1 (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0003)
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape, copy 2 (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0004)
    - Burger King, Now You Know Better, 1976-08-20
      1. Commencement; 2. Kid and Duke
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0005)
    - Burger King, Soul - female vocalist, circa 1976
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0006)
    - Burger King, misc., 1976-08-20
      Edit reel. Label is crossed out, but contains the following: Everything's a Whopper; Now You Know Better; Freshness; I Got This Thing; White Radio; Black Radio; Kids Campaign #1 Super Heros T.V.; Radio; Kids Campaign #2 Games; Characters; Jingle
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0005)
    - Burger King, out takes, undated
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0008)
    - Datsun, undated
      1. Get it right; 2. Make us feel like driving; 3. How would we ever get through; 4. Family; 5. Playboy; 6. Exit music
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0011)
    - Datsun rebate/radio, undated
      1. Sound of savings; 2. Booklet; 3. Dealer #1; 4. Dealer #2
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0012)
    - Kentucky Fried Chicken, undated
      Fun food you'll feel better about: 1. 60-second vocal; 2. 30-second vocal; 3. Moving Day; 4. Suzy; 5. Pushover; 6. Personnel; Make every meal a picnic: 1. 60-second vocal; 2. 60-second donut; 3. 30-second version I; 4. 30-second version II; 5. Personnel; 6. Radio 60-second; 7. Radio 30-second.
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0009)
    - Irving Sonn, reel 1, undated
      Friday's Child: 1. Man; 2. Duet; 3. Folk Rock; 4. Woman; 5. Duet; 6. Woman; Maybelline: 1. Kaleidoscope Eyes; 2. Saturday Night
      - Original quarter-inch open-reel audio tape (Box 6, Audio-reel RL01232-RR-0010)
    - Burger King presentation, undated
      - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL01232-CS-0003)
    - Radio and TV spots, unidentified, 1972-1976
      - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL01232-CS-0001)
    - Trident, "I Chew What I Want"; Wash 'n Dri, "Soap and Water to Go", undated
      - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL01232-CS-0002)
  - Moving image
    - Chase Manhattan: 1. Checkbook; 2. House and Home; 3. Chase Bank's Advantage, undated
      - Original 16mm film (Box 4, Film-reel RL01232-F16-0001)
    - Datsun presentation, reel 1, 1977-06-08
      "Dividend": 1. "Raining (F10)," 2. "Piggy Bank (810)," 3. "Li'l Hustler (King Cab)," 4. "Drive-in Bank"; "Get It Right": 1. "B210," 2. "280Z," 3. "King Cab," 4. "810," 5. "Honey Bee"; "What Would I Do?": 1. "Skiers (B210)," 2. "Family (810)," 3. "Playboy (280Z)," 4. "King Cab," 5. "Honey Bee"; "We Make You Feel": 1. "Receptionist (Honeybee)," 2. "Romantic (810)," 3. "Ballet (B210)," 4. "Carpenter (King Cab)," 5. "Opera (280Z)"; Reprise
      - Original 16mm film (Box 4, Film-reel RL01232-F16-0002)
    - Datsun presentation, reel 2, 1977-06-08
      - Original 16mm film (Box 4, Film-reel RL01232-F16-0003)
    - Irving Sonn, "Selling in the 70's," TV Reel, 1970s
      Datsun - Dali Wagon; Virgin Islands - Black Spokesman; Desk Top Lamps - Dancing Lamps; Isabel Rose - Pearls of the Douro; Rheingold - Syrian; Listerine - Longshoreman; Kellog's - Wake-Up; Schick - Barbarian Spokesman; Tuf Work Boots - Fashion Parade; Visine - Vignettes; Xerox - Can Puncture Demo; General Electric - Bull in the Lexan Shop; Playtex - Pearl Bailey; Camay - Princess Pignatelli; Trident - Whitey; Diet Pepsi - Zipper; American Motors - Shell; Vicks Vaporub - Breathing Jar; Egg Beaters - Limit; Gillette - Wet Head; Ultra Brite - How's Your Love Life; Buttertop Bread - Corn; Workclothes Burst - Mine; Johnson's Baby Shampoo - Brook; Coca-Cola - Country Sunshine; Wonder Bread - Farmer's Market
      - Original 16mm film (Box 4, Film-reel RL01232-F16-0004)
    - Irving Sonn - Reel #3, competitive commercials, undated
      - Original 16mm film (Box 4, Film-reel RL01232-F16-0005)
    - Ted Bates Adv. Toyota, 28 Kinescopes, undated
      - Original 16mm film (Box 4, Film-reel RL01232-F16-0006)
    - Ted Bates Presentation, 1977-11-07
      - Original Umatic videocassette (Box 6, Video-cassette RL01232-UM-0001, Digital-materials SET-0001, Video-file RL01232-Umatic_0001.mov)
    - Needham Bates, undated
      - Original VHS videocassette, part 1 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL01232-VHS-0001, Digital-materials SET-0001, Video-file RL01232-VHS-0001.mov)
      - Original VHS videocassette, part 2 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL01232-VHS-0002, Digital-materials SET-0001, Video-file RL01232-VHS-0002.mov)
- Award plaques and trophies, 1967-1977 and undated, 1 box
  Contains award plaques and trophies won by the Needham, Harper & Steers agency. Items arranged by format and listed alphabetically.
  - Plaques
    - Addy Awards (Box 5)
      - Consumer Magazines Ad Series, 1967 (Box 5)
      - Consumer Magazine Ad, black & white, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Direct Mail Piece, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Sales Promotion Material, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Undated
        - Consumer Magazine, black & white (Box 5)
        - Consumer Magazine, color (Box 5)
        - Trade Paper Campaign, black & white (Box 5)
    - Art Directors Club, New Jersey, undated (Box 5)
    - Dun's Review Advertising Excellence Award, Starch Score for Hertz Rent A Car, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Trophies
    - Addy Award
      - Direct Mail Piece, black & white, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Newspaper Advertisement, black & white, 1968 (Box 5)
      - American Radio Commercials Festival, Best Cosmetics, Toiletries, Pharmaceuticals, 1973 (Box 5)